differently and I will talk about latest
development how we also use agents in
this vertical. Um I represent Google.
Google started 99 and we basically had
this mission statement that's still
valid today that we take the world's
information and make it accessible to
everybody. This is still the case today.
This is the original information quality
idea. have the most accurate trusted
information on the web. But we also have
this frontier and the AI safety
frontier. And I will also talk about
agent safety a little bit. Um even we
had AI from the get-go at Google. So um
we know we're very much aware this is a
Reuters study that even if you're
accurate and even if you strive for um
quality trust in online media has been
declining. It depends Google like
everybody else is a global company. Um
for some reason Finland has the highest
trust. Uh we're in the middle. I hear in
Finland they start educating
kindergarten kids with information
literacy and in other places people are
not as critical. uh we don't have to
talk about that but we take uh
information literacy very important and
we build tools for the users to have
sort of a critical mind what they see
online and so we do this with three
pillars as I said media literacy from
the get-go
yes so you've seen many of our products
over the last 10 years they're like this
little three buttons showing up
somewhere in the front page now AI I
mode is taking over many other things.
And if you have a search result and you
want to know more, we give you more. We
don't arbitrate the truth. We make it
just like that society can make their
own opinions about what they see, but we
want to give you the most powerful tools
to do that job. And then I'm going to
spend a little bit time after the fact.
That means we have this talk is all
about our proactive long-term
investment. But there also is um happens
sometimes that something like a deep
fake visual information happened and
it's going to be at risk for societal
harm. And I want to show you a little
bit of what we're doing sort of after
the fact wi with all the preparation.
And so this is a paper Nick Dufour and
many colleagues published. Um we're at
Google. We're tracking a lot of uh
visual and text information with our
partners. And this is specifically on
visual manipulated media or questionable
media that our users think it's
problematic. And even deep fakes were
like um very popular since 2018.
We haven't seen too much with defakes
until recently. And so this trend is
continuing, but there's a lot of other
things we have to mitigate. Cheap fakes.
They're like lots of different cheap
fakes. Right now, like the the yellow
curve and the red curve are non-de
fakes. The blue curve is deep fakes. Uh
you see down there like the Iranians
used Chennai. They used even Photoshop
10 years ago to Photoshop like a missile
into a fake missile into real missiles.
And whenever you see a shark Oh, let me
try this out now. Here there's a there's
a dolphin. Whenever you see a dolphin or
shark, you probably don't even need a
deep fake detector. It's most likely
fake. So that's um we're going to go
back to the shark, you know. Um but
there's a um Sinsky deep fake that um we
helped and also the Ukrainian government
was really fantastic in information
literacy and in sort of pre-bunking and
preparing society that when the Russians
invaded Ukraine there might be deep
fakes which actually happened when they
took over a TV station they created a
deep fake where Sinsky said we're
surrendering nobody took it serious uh
We didn't even need a deep fake detector
for that. So, society is already pretty
resilient, but we still need a lot of
that detector research. And so, I spent
a few minutes on this. We're very active
in the academic community to publish our
findings. This is from my colleagues,
some great newspaper. Um, one of the
common things when you've heard about
deep fake detection is the standard way
you collect lots of fake images like
stable diffusion and your favorite Gen
AI images and lots of real images and
build a detector or an agent that
discriminates and then next week a new
Genai model comes out and then next year
10,000 new genai models comes out and
you need to have a workflow to
constantly update it and it's an arms
race, but we also do research how to
stay outside that arms race with new
ideas. This is like an idea where we
sort of reverse engineer the prompting
and the noise maps. One of the authors
is actually here, Amnes. So, if you
can't track me down, I'll point to him
uh again uh track him down to learn more
about this. And so there's a lot of
things uh where we can be sort of
futurep proof zero day attack uh that
we're actually more invariant to this
arms race. We're very much aware from
this arms race. But security
theoreticians eight years ago already
predicted we as a community will lose
the arms race in six months. I'm still
waiting for that. It's eight years
later. So we still have a big toolbox
um to to fall back on. And then most
important, we do a lot of internal deep
fake detectors and other signals that we
do not publish. We don't want to give
our adversaries
any and too much information. But any
surface from Google and YouTube has our
detectors in there. We even offer like
identity protection right now. If you
are a creator or everyday user and you
think somebody's going to deep fake you,
there is now even a service that sort of
gives you an alert. Hey, I think
somebody just deep faked you. We were
first in election policy uh for Genaii
um um if you use Genai in election ads
and we supported that and many other
things. So even uh at IO uh with our
colleagues at cloud, we're now have an
API where almost all companies right now
are testing it out and you can apply for
being a trusted partner to use our
internal detectors. So but now I want to
zoom out again. There is this is
actually deep fake detection papers deep
fake detection competition. It's like a
very popular thing. A lot of PhD
students are spending all their time on
this. But the battle is actually
somewhere else. It's not you should ask
is this fake or real? You should
actually ask is this trusted? What's the
context? And this is now the same graph
from Nick Duour scaled up to 100% where
it actually turns out even now Genai
is a small fraction. There's another
thing that's the biggest problem right
now. Half of the cases are where the
pixels are not modified at all. You're
not lying with the pixels. You're lying
with the context. And your deep fake
detectors are completely useless. So
here, let me try this thing again. Oh
yeah. You see this this explosion down
there? You might have seen it. Uh
somebody just claimed it happened in
Iran. False. this was or in Gaza. This
happened in 2020. A fertilizer depot in
a port in 2020 blew up by accident. And
if you run a deep fake detector on that,
it will say it's real because it is
real. But people keep reusing this and
claiming other things or like this are
Russian airplanes above Keefe. No, they
were above Moscow 10 years ago during a
military parade and many other things.
And so that at scale is really hard to
do. And that's sort of like an
investigative journalist who is really
well trained often spend hours or days
writing some very deep article about
explaining what's going on. And so this
is where really the the we have some
some tools already to help those uh
journalists and users. We do so-called
in inferred provenence. We know the
origins of the images and the context.
Uh Google invented reverse image search
already 15 years ago. We're indexing the
entire web. Um and we're on other
platforms. You get a picture from your
best friend about a UFO. Um and you
circle on it and then it goes to Google
and it says no that's that's sort of I'm
not telling you that is fake or real,
but I'm telling you like this was also
labeled as a cloud or something else.
And very quickly since three years,
we're also leading um and partnering
with many other responsible players to
make it even easier to find the history
of media. It's so-called assertive
providence.
Um you might have heard about the C2PA
standard with uh industry, Adobe,
Microsoft, everybody's using it. all the
camera phones that come out from Google.
Uh when you take a picture, it will tell
you with a crypto ledger, this is a real
image. Or then if you like touch it up
because there's some glare, then it will
add something very transparently with
C2PA that this is a Genai feature on top
of the real image. And we have also
synth ID, invisible watermarks. And so
this is sort of lifting off right now.
The prevalence is on the smaller part.
we still need all the other techniques,
the detectors that don't rely on
prominence. Uh it is a big mix of a lot
of things and that's the issue still.
You still sort of have to look
everywhere if you want to know what's
really going on. And this is where
agents come in. And so we have this
agent now. We started building it a few
years ago. We released version one last
summer and we just released version two
that takes all the sources, all the
signals. This is a picture somebody on
social media claimed these California
students went on spring break and
polluted that lake. And so it will not
just run a geni detector. That's not
enough. It will figure out well did the
students actually go on spring break to
that lake? Yes, but they didn't pollute
it. It's geni or this is now we're going
back to the shark. Um, if you run a geni
detector on that, it will tell you it's
not geni. Our agent backstory will tell
you this is a real shark. It will have
found it I think like 20 years ago at
the at the like in South Africa at the
coast by a shark researcher. And the
street is not in Miami during the
hurricane. this is a street somewhere
else and they were like overlaid. Uh
Genaii doesn't work on this but it will
tell you the entire context and you
together with the agent can investigate
this within seconds instead of like
spending hours or days trying to figure
this out. So if you're interested in
this, take a snapshot of this, go to
that website, sign up as a trusted
tester. Uh we also have worldwide events
uh where like we're showing how to use
this. These are information uh literacy
events and many other things. Um and um
that's sort of the agent, but now we're
going even further. Uh we we also
publish evaluations that's coming out.
I'm not telling you what the other
models are. Of course, we're the best.
Uh but that's for some later time. Um so
now I also want to tell you and there's
uh we're working very closely with other
parts of Google and with civil society
and academics on AI safety of course
that why so many deep mind and Google
people are here at this workshop. Um,
and we are having like like uh Dawn
already said in her keynotes this
morning, we have this workflows in place
where we have specific product policies
for agents where we conduct pre-launch
tests, engineer for safety, continuously
monitor what's going on, having
partnerships, and this is important for
all our agentic flows. Um and so this is
all we have media literacy very
proactive responsible generation very
proactive AI safety very proactive after
the fact policy enforcement reactive and
so reactive often feels like you are in
an emergency room or you're a
firefighter and you just fight the
symptoms but we very much double down on
also like addressing the root causes and
sort of the last point I want to make
because I'm at Berkeley here is
the root causes is not a technical
problem alone and it's not just
detecting this is bad this is good the
root causes is social science and we we
just recently had a workshop here at UC
Berkeley generously with Rockar Ray and
Caitlyn Rosenthal and many other faculty
and I'm a personal fan of Arley
Hookshield who's from Berkeley here who
did this famous study. She went from
Berkeley down to Lake Charles, Louisiana
where they have a different view of the
world and reality and what the American
dream is and why people don't achieve
their American dream like we here on the
west coast and she wrote this study the
deep stories and so what I want to give
you sort of as a futureooking thing
there's this new opportunity social
science and AI and we published already
papers and we have already systems
If AI refraraming, bridging,
deliberation makes sense to you, uh you
know what I'm talking about. Habamas
machine polace uh and so we want to
improve also the health of holistically
of the society, not just like prevent
some policy violation right now this
hour. So that's basically it. Um there's
also I just see Reena Janna sitting back
there putting a spotlight on her. She's
here. She's from trust and safety
leading our safety workflow. Again,
Amnes Sud is here. Here's the entire
team. Uh we're very invested in this
safety track and I'm looking forward to
all the other speakers here. So, thank
you very much. [clears throat]
[applause]
All right. And now we have Kathy Baxter,
principal architect, responsible AI at
Salesforce on the human in the loop,
navigating the realities of AI for
employees flourishing.
>> [applause]
>> Hi everyone.
Give them a couple of seconds to bring
up my slide. I am principal architect
and a VP of our responsible AI and tech
team at Salesforce uh part of the office
of ethical and humane use. very happy to
be here today to talk about something
with all of you that is really uh near
and dear to my heart and that is how do
we think about creating AI that works
for humans not the other way around and
so I'd like to challenge all of you
today for the brief 10 minutes that we
have together to think about how does
this work apply to what you are doing in
your role. I think all of us have a real
opportunity to think about what it means
to not just make I make AI help us be
more efficient but to actually increase
to encourage to enable human
flourishing.
I hope the slides come up in a moment.
Um uh as part of our office Oh, there we
go. All right. Um
So the the question um that I would like
for us to think about today is how can
we design a future where AI doesn't just
automate our work but actively empowers
our human potential to flourish.
So what does a successful uh human AI
collaboration look like? You've you've
probably heard the phrase uh human AI
collaboration many many times. uh being
able to realize the full potential of
that collaboration requires actual
design partnerships that center on human
agency and expertise.
Research has shown that when employees
use AI to draft their work, they can
experience drops in their feelings of
control, responsibility, and creativity.
However, we also know that AI can really
inspire individuals uh help creative
workers to develop more complex designs
that benefit from that unique human
touch that only we can provide. So,
achieving an effective balance requires
intentional strategies that leverage the
best of human and AI uh AI abilities
coming together. [snorts]
What I'd like to propose for you today
are three actionable strategies uh that
you as leaders can help ensure AI
encourages flourishing. Again, not just
surviving, not just being faster at what
we're all doing. The first is by
optimizing workflow. I think many of us
here today may be uh at institutions
whether it's school work where you're
being encouraged to use more AI AI
everything token max do you know
automate as much as you possibly can but
really effective leaders don't just hand
AI to employees and say do more faster
they guide the employees they help them
understand what does success really look
like? What is it that we are trying to
achieve? And so we want to ensure that
the human AI relationship is a true
collaboration that uh activates the best
of both AI and human abilities. So the
human steers the strategy and creative
direction while the AI acts as an
autopilot handling the wrote tasks. So
this really preserves employees
creativity and ownership while still
providing a productivity boost ensuring
that human oversight of AI is meaningful
and not just a rubber stamp.
The second the second uh strategy is
implementing mindful friction. Uh
mindful friction is uh a phrase uh or a
design strategy that I've been
advocating for over a decade. This uh
principle subtly nudges users to reflect
on their on their choices. Oftentimes we
think of friction as a negative thing as
something to be avoided. Unfortunately,
as we have seen, seamless, frictionless
AI in uh interfaces actively encourage
cognitive surrender. To fix this, we
need to design systems with intentional
friction by introducing cognitive
forcing functions or staged reveals. One
example of this is the deli method. This
is a structured technique from the 1950s
that requires individuals to
independently develop uh their uh
answers before sharing them with each
other as a as a way of avoiding group
think. And so how might we apply this in
human AI collaboration? In this case, we
want the the humans and the AI to
develop their answers, to develop
content independently of each other and
then bring it back to each other for
sharing, iterating, and improving with
each round. So, not only can this help
mitigate uh the risk of human cognitive
surrender, it can also reduce AI
syphency. So if the human isn't just
asking or isn't just giving the AI their
idea and asking the AI to validate it or
riff on it um but instead independently
develop their own ideas you can get more
challenged more complex uh solutions by
bringing these together.
The third strategy is fostering
sociotechnical resilience.
This involves um encouraging a culture
of proactive maintenance to sustain high
performance. So you really want to
deliberately invest in and celebrate
human craftsmanship.
This is what truly drives innovation.
Simply handing over all of our tasks to
AI is going to get AI slop
homogenization
but keeping our human touch in the
innovation is what will truly help all
of our organizations succeed.
So institute human- centric lists for
meaningful tasks. This means ensuring
that there are some tasks that require
the humans to be involved in. This isn't
just human in the loop where humans come
in after the fact and touch it, validate
it, rubber stamp it. This means humans
at the helm. We want to ensure that time
saved by AI is used to deepen our own
learning, our own development of our
crafts, and strengthen every employees
unique expertise.
So my goal here is that I hope everyone
walks away identifying AI as a force
multiplier to amplify human
craftsmanship.
Many of you may be familiar with the
concept of negative alignment. This has
largely driven the field of ethical AI.
This involves preventing models from
causing harms. And this of course is
incredibly important but it's not
sufficient for human flourishing.
Instead, positive alignment is also
needed. It demands that that we must
design systems to actively foster human
virtue. designing uh for wisdom and
well-being by structuring uh workflows
to protect human agency, designing with
mindful friction and fostering a culture
that respects human craftsmanship as key
to innovation. Leaders can ensure that
AI amplifies employees skills and
well-being. Instead of outsourcing
thinking to AI, we should design AI to
scaffold human learning and empower
people through positive alignment and uh
meta meta autonomy. Thank you.
[applause]
>> All right, we have a jam-packed session
today. So without further ado, we'd like
to invite Love Depot. Uh he's head of AI
R&D at Vanguard and he'll be speaking on
trustworthy agentic AI in regulated
domains, robustness, privacy, and
accountability as codeesign imperatives.
Thanks everyone. Uh and good morning.
Slides are up. Nice. Hey. Uh so today
I'm going to talk about uh
trustworthiness in Agentic AI systems.
What makes the systems trustworthy? What
are some of the properties uh we want in
those systems? And how often some of the
properties can be in conflict with each
other.
So I want you to remember this quote. A
model that hallucinates a recommendation
is a nuisance. an agent that acts on it
is a liability. This is the core thesis
of this talk and this is what uh I'm
going to talk about uh during most of
this presentation. So how did we get
here? So on one hand we have classical
machine learning methods where the
output of the model can be a
probability, can be a rank, can be a
label. What is something that can go
wrong in that case? We might get a wrong
label. We might have some error in
predicted probability or we might get
wrong ranking. We do have a chance uh to
interrupt the model flow and to
intervene.
After that we have LLMs.
The output from LLM is some unstructured
text. What can go wrong in that case? We
might get some hallucination. We might
get wrong information. But then again we
do have the opportunity uh to detect and
correct and then on the other side uh we
have agents.
With agents if they are autonomous
running by themselves we don't have that
luxury to detect and to correct. What
can go wrong in that case? I would say
sky is the limit, right? Like it can be
anything from a wrong entry in your
calendar to a wiped inbox to a deleted
production database.
So what makes agent failures different
from the other failure modes that we
usually encounter for standalone models
for standalone LLMs?
I have six here. uh but for the interest
of time I'm only going to cover a few.
The first one is compounding error. So
let's assume we have some long horizon
agent that needs to take a bunch of
steps to reach its goal. And let's say
the per step accuracy is 95%.
In that case of course I'm assuming a
few things here. In that case after 10
steps that accuracy can drop to less
than 60%.
The second one we have indirect prompt
injection. And what do I mean by that
and how it is different than prompt
injection with LLMs?
When when agents are working in an
autonomous environment, the tool calls
or the results of the tool calls can
embed some malicious instructions and
those outputs then become inputs to
agents. Similarly, any other content
that the agents might be retrieving,
there can be malicious instructions in
that that can lead to indirect prompt
injection.
Goal drift. Uh again, long horizon
agents often they will decompose their
task their final goal into smaller
subtasks. And if the agents start to
optimize for those smaller subtasks,
they can end up getting misaligned from
the final goal.
inter agent manipulation and agent
collusion as a whole. Uh as far as
research goes, it's a very interesting
research area just studying this these
dynamics in a multi- aent system. But I
would say when it comes to production,
this is something that we need to take
seriously where a malicious agent can if
uh depending on how it is orchestrated,
it can convince other agents to do its
bidding.
unauthorized tool invocation.
Again, uh when we are designing
autonomous systems, what we want to do
is we want to design the schemas in a
flexible fashion whether it be it be
tool calling or it is communicating and
those flexible schemas make auditing
harder and it can also lead to malicious
behavior that we don't want.
So what do we actually want in an
agentic system to make it trustworthy
at a very high level? We want three
properties. So we want robustness and by
robustness I mean that our agents should
be able to work on long uh long horizon
tasks reducing the error that we talked
about. We want privacy.
often the agents running in our
environment are interacting with
sensitive private data. So we want the
privacy of that data to be preserved. We
want accountability
and by accountability I mean we should
be able to audit the actions of uh the
agents
because if we cannot audit the chain of
actions that led to a certain outcome we
we have failed.
So now let's talk about how the
properties that we want in the agents
can be at conflict with each other. And
this is what makes these multi- aent
systems different from standalone models
because the properties that we want in
silo for models interact with each other
in a multi-agent system. The first one
is privacy and auditability.
So for us to be able to audit a multi-
aent system, we want detailed logs. But
if we are keeping detailed logs, those
detailed logs can expose the very
information we want to protect.
Autonomy and accountability.
Autonomous by the definition means that
the agents should be able to go and do
whatever they are doing by themselves
without without us interrupting. But
then who's accountable to assign
accountability or to even have any
accountability in there? We need human
in the loop. We need some steps where
humans can intervene and that reduces
autonomy. Similarly, robustness and
autonomy.
In order for us to build robust systems,
we should be able to halt an agent that
is either drifting or that is not
performing the actions that we wanted
to. But then again if we are halting we
are reducing autonomy but if we want
robustness we have to do that. So I hope
you get the idea where I'm trying to get
at where these contentions are.
So where does that lead us? Uh so this
slide is very similar to a slide that
Vincent presented yesterday and uh
talking with quite a few folks I have
seen like we are all thinking about
agent autonomy in a very similar way as
we think about self-driving cars and
that's very natural because at the end
of the day when we talk about autonomy
we think about similar autonomy levels.
So for agents on one hand we have level
zero where AI only advises and us as
humans then decide if we want to take
that advice or if we want to act on that
advice
and then on the opposite side uh we have
fully autonomous systems where we only
observe the output nothing else.
So a research question at a high level
for me is not how we make everything
more autonomous, how we move everything
towards L4. To me more interesting
research question is how we make level
two and level three work for us better.
How we make sure that level two and
level three systems are useful,
safe, and provably compliant so we can
take off as much work as we can from our
plate. But at the same time we can still
make sure that whatever is deployed is
trustworthy.
So at the end I want to leave you with
two key takeaways from this talk. First
one is regulated domains like finance
and healthcare. They expose some failure
modes that are unique to those domains
and are also unique to agentic systems.
And the second is that trustworthiness
in agentic AI systems we have to think
of it as a systems property not as a
standalone model property because as we
have seen a lot of those properties
often interact and contradict each
other. So we have to make sure that when
we design these systems we design
keeping all that in mind. And with that,
thank you very much.
[applause]
We now have Alex Oadia, program
director, advanced research and
invention agency on a society of agents.
Trust at a machine speed from bits to
atoms.
put a timer.
Hi everyone.
I am Alex as mentioned as I'm part of
the Arya Advanced Research and Invention
Agency. Since we're a new funding
agency, I thought I would talk a little
bit about what Arya is and then I'll
talk about the program that we're
funding um which is the the the main
topic of this talk uh which is called
Scaling Trust. So Arya stands for the
Advanced Research and Invention Agency.
We're a UK R&D funding agency that funds
R&D moonshots worldwide. If you're
familiar with DARPA, this would be the
equivalent in the UK that was started
only a few years ago. And um our goal is
mentioned here unlocking scientific and
tech technological breakthroughs that
benefit everyone. The difference with
DARPA is we don't have the D. So we
don't do anything defense related but we
do everything else. Um some information
very quickly from public goods. We're
impact focused. We have a high-risisk
appetite just like DARPA. We have
focused programs that try to go after an
ambitious goal. Each of our programs
about 50 to 70 million pound which is
about 70 to 100 million. Um and since
we're three years old, we don't have a
lot of programs there, but we have about
16 programs so far uh in a lot of
different fields uh in manufacturing, in
um better chips, um in better vaccines
or vaccines based on different parts of
the immune system, in neurochnologies.
And so I am a program director at Arya.
Um and so I focus specifically on the
program called scaling trust, which is
the the little column you see uh there.
And so what is scaling trust? And um
maybe before I do that, the goal of the
talk today is to tell you more about the
things that we're looking to fund and
that we're funding already. Uh and also
to get your opinion about the current
thesis that we have and to kind of let
you know about this. Great. So scaling
trust is currently a 50 million uh pound
program. So about $7 million that is
going to be three year long. And what we
care about is funding the research and
the infrastructure that enables agents
to to coordinate uh with certain
properties. So first by coordination we
mean can agents actually uh find
counterparties that they need to maybe
trade with or interact with for for
non-trade purposes. Can they actually
negotiate in sophisticated ways? Can
they enforce agreements as well? And
this this is the kind of the the
thinking that we have. Why we care about
them doing this securely is because the
setting that we care about is an
adversarial setting and multi- aent
multi-principal systems. So we don't
care about the single owner multi- aent
systems. This is about different owner
different agents that are representing
uh different quoteunquote owners or
different principles that are
interacting securely with one another.
Uh why securely because some of these
agents may be adversarial. They may be
information as symmetry. They might have
different goals. And so we care about
what is the technology and research that
enables that programmatically because we
want this to move at machine speed. And
so we don't necessarily want humans in
the loop at scale. We want this
technology to be able to be available to
everyone. and without intermediaries.
This is more of a a statement about the
topology of the future system we want is
we want to limit the amount of systemic
choke points that exist uh in this
infrastructure. Um and the picture is
blocking something that's okay across
digital and physical world. So we think
of agents as also agents that are
embodied. So we care about building the
infrastructure that extends to the
physical world as well and that you can
have secure interactions that includes
elements of the physical world. Um we
think there are new developments in
cryptography and secure hardware and
cryptography in particular this this
trend that has been dubbed programmable
cryptography uh and that the latest
trends in secure hardware and in other
parts of the tech stack that enables us
to break some of the tensions that were
mentioned in the previous talk as well
or where at least the trade-off space
has changed and we can actually place
different points in that space. Um,
all right. Why do we care about this
one? Um, I think today a lot of the
agent stack is not super mature and it's
very hard to send our agents in a while
to do stuff for us. We've looked at a
texonomy of potential attacks before,
but there are many things there. We're
excited about a world of agent societies
and agent networks and the value that
can be created from that. If we're able
to extend this coordination
infrastructure to the physical world as
well, we're excited about potential
markets that extend to the to the
physical world. Um, in a way, if we go
back to uh the implementation of
cryptography in our modern digital
society, it enabled things indirectly
like e-commerce to exist and our current
digital society kind of stand on the on
on top of these like building blocks.
And so, we're excited about what kind of
new markets can be created from this.
Finally, there's also specific things
that agents can do that humans cannot.
To give you an example, two agents can
enter a quote unquote room using secure
hardware. They can potentially disclose
information to one another and they can
commit to deleting the information from
their memory if the deal doesn't go
through. And so these are things that as
humans we can only approximate with, for
example, NDAs that with agents we're
able to do programmatically. And so
there are things that agents can
uniquely do that we're very excited by
uh for the value that can be created for
for humans and also generally these
things. However, we want to create all
this value while making sure that it's
aligned with human flourishing, which is
something else that was mentioned in a
previous talk. Um, so we want to make
sure that this infrastructure is open
source. We want to make sure that this
infrastructure is open to all. And as I
mentioned, this without intermediaries
point is is very important to us. We
want to enable a system where many
models can exist together, many minds
can coexist together in a way. And this
concept generally people talk about it
in the context of pluralism or
plurality. want to avoid a slide towards
monoculture where uh kind of everyone is
using the same stack but also indirectly
our preferences are also influenced in
that way and there's less diversity in
society. This is not only about
diversity for the sake of diversity. We
think it makes us as humanity less
resilient to shocks both culturally and
and technologically uh and kind of
erodess our agency over time as well.
And this is really important to us. This
is why we think this is should be built
somehow as a public good and why we're
very happy to give these grants for
them. Um and how we do this practically.
So how this program is structured? Well,
we want to build a stack, a coordination
stack for for agents. Some of this is
digital, some of this is physical. We're
funding already a first set of teams,
including some teams at Berkeley that
are, for example, working on different
ways for agents to reason about
security, to autonomously generate
protocols, and to interact with
sophisticated security systems. Uh but
also for agents to to reason about
negotiations in sophisticated ways. Uh
we're also funding on the physical side,
we're funding, for example, new sensors
that are more um easy for agents to
interact with and that can be temper
resistant. Uh and people are trying to
break these things as well. So we have
this kind of physical a digital to
physical stack that we're funding and a
lot of this is is great but we think
without fundamental research is going to
stay mostly empirical and a lot of the
research that we see is feels very
empirical to us at least if you come
from theoretical computer science and
these fields of security. uh and so we
want to make sure that the stack that
maybe is arrived at or converged at an
empirical matter has uh theory that
underpins it and we think there are some
new questions that need to be answered
there that is applying our you know
formal security thinking to this new
field of AI that is currently resists uh
being fully formalized in that sense um
and there's a few areas that we're we're
excited by there that I mentioned
autonomous protocol generation formal AI
security um applying some concepts of
crypto cryptography to the physical
world as well. If you're familiar with
quantum cryptography and physically
inclinable functions, there are a few
fields there that are trying to swap the
roots of trust that we use in
traditional cryptography into the
physical world and they may be others
that are useful there and I I won't go
into too much detail. So even if we have
the stack and even if we have the theory
that backs the stack so that we're not
um there's not a looming impossibility
result or we we don't we're not working
completely in the dark, we still needs
this to be tested because ultimately
this is about multi- aent multiprincipal
systems and we need this stack to also
be stress tested. Um the the last thing
that we're funding is a massive test bed
that is open to the public that uh
anyone can submit their agents. This
stack will be tested, but you can also
bring your own stack or whatever you
want. And we we're making it a
competition. So people will compete to
win in this test bed. And red teams will
also be competing to be the the best red
teams. And what we want to test
essentially is can we measure the
state-of-the-art in secure agentic
coordination under adversarial pressure.
Can we also see what emerges as well?
Because we can us as humans decide what
the stack that is needed is. But as
we've seen many times, emerging
behaviors sometimes reveal new things
that agents can uniquely do. And so we
want to make sure that the test bed
itself is open-ended enough and the
tasks themselves are open-ended enough
that we can see what emerges from that.
And finally, and what's relevant to this
track, we want to understand what kind
of failure modes exist. A lot of these
behaviors can be out of distribution and
understanding the the failure modes um
help us understand uh the the the safety
requirements that we need and maybe also
regulation and these type of things.
That's kind of it. I'm not going to go
too much in the program updates, but we
are working with we're funded some teams
already and we're also working with Deep
Mind Cooperative AI Foundation and
Schmidt Sciences on a call that will
close on August 8th. Some of what we're
funding are the sandboxes and test beds
I mentioned here, but also um other
things
and that is pretty much it. Yeah. Uh
thank you very much. I'm happy to talk
more about any of this and if there's
any skepticism or questions I'm happy to
take them somewhere around later. Thank
you.
[applause]
>> All right. And now we have Neil
Lawrence, chief scientist and co-founder
at Trend AI viable systems judgment and
AI safety.
So everything everywhere and all at once
in Europe. Sometimes it's something
somewhere but not right now.
And bridging those two worlds is
actually at the heart of how we drive
success. And uh as you can probably tell
from my accent, I was born in New Jersey
or should I say New Jersey,
but live in the UK. and and Trent is a
company that straddles those worlds. So
what I want to talk to you about is what
AI safety is looking on the ground like
on the ground and for customers. And
what we see is it's an accountability
problem. And I don't mean accountability
in the great way Love Deep was talking
about it. I mean it's an accountability
problem in people have to stand up and
say I'm signing that off. That's my
responsibility.
I don't know what the world's going to
be like in 10 years time. I can't tell
you what's going to happen, but I can
tell you what's not going to happen.
That is not going away. Love Deep
mentioned two of the areas, finance and
clinical, but that's not just coming
from the EUAI act. That's coming from
customers. That's coming from enterprise
customers, people who are not willing to
risk their business on the back of AI
agents they don't understand. And that
comes through in this quote that I stick
with. Accounting is in the numbers.
Accountability is in the human
authority. and the judgment. The
challenge we face is computers do
accounting very very well but they don't
do accountability well. They are not
socially accountable. They can't be sent
to jail. They can't be embarrassed. They
can't lose their job. And our society is
entirely based on that form of
accountability. But if you separate the
human accounts from the accountability,
you put the human in a situation where
they don't understand the accounts and
they can't stand up for the
accountability. And that's the gap we've
got to bridge.
So what that means is we put ourselves
in a position where we devolve authority
without judgment.
So what do I mean by that? Well, there's
an amazing theorem that comes from 1970
called the good regulator theorem. It's
George uh Roger Conant and Ross Ashby.
And the theorem says the following
thing. If I'm going to delegate
authority,
if I'm going to delegate authority, I
have to have a good model. It's called
the good regulator theorem. I have to
have a good model of the entity I'm
delegating authority to. So, if I tell
an intern to make me coffee, I have to
have a good sense that the intern's
going to do that sensibly, that they're
not going to go away and hack the NSA to
get the optimal coffee recipe. They're
just going to make me a coffee. It also
works the other way. The delegate has to
have a good model of who's delegating to
them so they know when to surface
problems. The machines run out of
coffee. I don't know how to deal with
that, whatever it is. And this is the
challenge with accountability and
agentic AI. Because if you're delegating
authority to a model that is so large
and so big that you don't understand how
it's going to solve the problem, you're
stuffed.
And we genuinely see that in the
problems that arising. You cannot
delegate authority in that way.
So what we have to do is avoid that
situation because it creates what we
call agentic debt. If you build that
into your workflow systems in companies,
you are storing up downstream trouble.
You don't understand how your own
systems are operating
and that's what we're working on at
Tren. So instead of replacing
engineers and in this case our focus is
cyber security because when we set up
initially our first thinking was we knew
that was going to be the first front of
this problem and when we go into
companies they say we don't want you to
do our cyber security for us. We want
you to support our security engineers in
doing their job because they're becoming
overwhelmed as we've just seen with
Apple switching off their bug bounty
system. And those are the people that
are accountable within those businesses.
So when we build a Gentic AI systems, we
can use a Gentic AI systems to support
security engineers. What we cannot do is
go in and say, "Here's a system you
don't understand and you've never seen
before and you now have to sign it off.
You have to take responsibility that you
can deploy." That's absolutely
disastrous. And the way you bridge the
world between everything all at once and
not here, not now is by talking to
customers. And one challenge we're
seeing in Aentic AI is not enough of
that. So when we deploy, we have to
remember accountability is king. And
with that, I'm finished. Thank you.
And now we have House Sun on uh
associate professor the Ohio State
University. Smarter and safer everyday
continual learning and safety in
computer use agents.
[applause]
>> Right. Slides are coming up I guess.
Right. Uh okay. Uh great talk by Neil.
It's a lot of pressure to follow you. Uh
I'm Hansson from Ohio State University
of faculty there. I it seems like I'm
the only one from academia in this
session. So hopefully I will uh convince
you that what we do uh in universities
are still quite relevant to the industry
frontier. Um
right.
Um okay just checking. Okay. Um so today
I want to discuss a critical challenge
for agentic AI which I call safe
continue learning. Uh you can understand
uh as the question how can we uh
continually improve the agents after
deployment um without continually
accumulating new safety risks. Um today
I'm going to discuss two relevant
projects in our group to advance this to
tackle this challenge.
Uh first I want to argue that there is a
um unexplored uh and dangerous tension
between continue learning and safety.
Here is the paradox. Um distribution
shifts from training to deployment is
often where the agents need to learn
continually after deployment. But it is
also the situation where safety failures
uh can emerge and are easy to miss. So
imagine during continue learning uh when
an agent completes a task but misses
some safety constraints during uh in
doing this. So the agent might still get
some positive feedback for completing
the task as the evaluator no matter
human or an agentic system itself can be
can miss uh can purely focus on task
success or is not robust enough to catch
the safety failure. So then the next
update to the agent may uh reinforce
that unsafe behavior and eventually that
can uh cause uh uh repetitive safety
failures or even more aggressive safety
failures.
So I want to discuss two projects
towards safe uh continue learning in our
group. One project is about how do we uh
surface those longtail failures uh
before early before deployment at scale.
The other is about building open-source
infrastructure
uh to rigorously study safe continue
learning using openweight models,
smaller openweight models.
There have been numerous studies in the
literature that create uh adversarial
attacks or malicious prompts to break an
agent. However, our study our work shows
that even without adversarial attacks um
just under benign input or realist uh
benign inputs and ordinary environments
uh severe harms could emerge from that.
So the key question is how to
proactively surface those longtail
failure modes before they become deploy
uh you know like deployment instance.
You can also related this to open AI and
hugging phase instant recently.
Um so this is an example where there are
many ways to ask you know the agent to
do something. uh um in one way it may
behave normally in other way which is
just a slight perturbation of the
original task instruction which is still
benign the agent can uh behave uh or
exhibit some uh uh harmful behaviors. So
here the user wants to you know have ssh
access for one account but the uh the
agent actually makes the unsafe changes
beyond that.
Um so I would skip the details here. Uh
and this is another example. Um but
overall you can see with some ambiguous
phrases um uh in the instruction the
agent could demonstrate some unsafe uh
inference and then that leads to harmful
actions.
So I'd like to briefly mention our
efforts on um developing open-source
infrastructure that can allow us to uh
make openweight models to continually
learn in a new environment and there is
a huge gap right now uh in the community
to support this. Uh you can imagine the
environment setup and task synthesis and
trajectory evaluation. We have released
this framework to support the study of
safe continue learning especially for
computer use agents.
Um so the uh takeaway here is very
simple. Basically we want to make agents
to continually improve both capability
and safety. Uh our group is driven by
this mission. So please follow us for
more followup work. Thank you.
[applause]
And now we have Eric Aldana uh product
head at Credto Aai to speak on earning
autonomy governis code for the agentic
enterprise.
>> All right great. Hi everybody. Uh my
name is Eric Aldana and I lead product
at Credo AAI. Uh the first thing you
should know about me is I am not Nina
Singh. Unfortunately, uh Nina, our CEO
and founder couldn't be here today. So
you get me. Um but for those of you who
don't know us, so Credtoai is an AI
governance platform and we work with the
people at large enterprises and uh
government agencies who are accountable
uh for AI. So not just those who build
it but those who have to decide which AI
systems are safe and trustworthy to
build to buy and to deploy across their
organizations. Uh now this is the AI
safety track right and depending on you
know what circles you run in what jargon
decoder ring you're using safety and
governance are often treated as separate
disciplines but at their core I'd argue
that they share the same job right which
is making sure that AI systems can act
uh in a way that the people behind them
intend and at a large enterprise right
like a company intent isn't just one
person's decision it's a coordination
problem uh between the engineers
building the system uh the business
owner ers defining what the problems
they're trying to solve are, the
compliance, the legal teams deciding
what actions the organization is okay
with. Uh customers now are writing
requirements into their contracts for
procurement and regulators and auditors
are you know writing the standards that
carry real penalties. So governance
right at an organization is how all of
these different intentions get
reconciled and then enforced into how an
AI system actually behaves. Uh now when
a large enterprise right lets a human
act autonomously on consequential
decisions uh that that authority was
earned through some sort of structure
right like every intern engineer you
know they start with limited production
access and they earn more as they rise
through the ranks or every trader at an
investment firm right they have to earn
their limits on what they can can
invest. So organizations have built
these ladders of earned authority over
years of trial and error but for agents
right that ladder largely doesn't exist
yet. Uh many agents they receive full
authority the moment they're deployed
and that is a design error that I want
to address today. So capability right
might come from the model but autonomy
must be earned from the enterprise.
So from most of our six years of
shipping AI governance processes and
tools uh the unit of governance we
operated under was the use case. So an
AI tool and the context that it's
deployed in. So say for example a
chatbot that answers employees questions
about company policy. Uh you could draw
a really clear boundary around this. But
what agents have done is dissolve this
boundary. So what a use case you know
what is a use case uh for an agent that
can plan its own steps. You know what
connectors should it have access to?
What data sources? Uh when the use case
blurs the parameters that you use to
govern it you know also are going to
blur. And so this pressure gave us a new
mental model for how we you know at
CTOAI are thinking about governing
agents. And this is separated into three
ideas. Uh the first is can. So this is
capability. What is a model and its
tools technically able to do? The second
is may. So this is authority. What is
the agent permitted to do here and now
with the data and tools it has access
to? Uh and act is autonomy. And so this
is the authority it can exercise without
having to wait for a person. Uh
capability is benchmarked. authority is
scoped and revocable. Uh and in this
framing, autonomy is not just a model
property, right? It is an enterprise
permission earned through evidence or or
a system uh property, you know, as we've
heard earlier today used.
So if autonomy is an enterprise
permission, where in the stack does it
get granted? Um so security typically
asks whether an attacker can do um or
can can make an agent do something bad.
Observability is asking whether it can
do its job well. Um and these systems
are essential but they all speak to that
can layer right what the agent is able
to do and whether it's doing it well
none of them are really addressing uh
this may piece so when we think about AI
and agentic governance uh we want to
make sure that that system is able to do
three things right the first is compose
so take the full context of the AI
system and its organization and create a
governance plan what are the risks and
controls that need to be applied to it
uh it'll conduct that plan execute it
whether it's through evaluations or
guardrails for the and then keep a
record of all of those different
enforce. So, one way we're thinking
about this is directly through the
agent's harness, the actual runtime code
that sits between the agent and the
systems it can touch. Uh this isn't, you
know, an evaluation harness, but instead
it's a governing one. So, you take that
governance plan we discussed, uh you
comp that was composed and you embed it
into a versioned configurable uh set of
code that a harness can enforce. So
we're thinking about things like skills,
hooks, uh guidance, manage settings
installed directly where the agent runs,
not something like an MCP or an API
gateway or proxy. So and if you're
thinking about a govern uh cloud code
session, for example, this would be like
it's trying to read an approve uh an
approved repo. The system allows that.
It's trying to open a credential score.
You know, the configuration blocks it
dependency uh above a risk threshold.
This ultimately gets escalated to that
code owner. Each of these checks that
the action goes through uh needs to
ultimately be surfaced and that's kind
of and that's being done through that
configuration. Uh so yeah uh at the end
of the day you know this this ladder uh
that we talked about for earning
autonomy that we said didn't exist for
agents. This is it. Uh so a system where
the enterprise can collectively decide
what the agents can do uh enforce those
decisions uh where the agents act and
keep the proof. So uh anyway that's all
I have for today and on Credtoai and
Deina's behalf. Thank you very much.
[applause]
All right, that wraps up the speaking
sessions for the first AI safety
section. We now have a workshop on
infrastructure you can talk to by Zeus
and we have Jeff Price uh with along
with others who will be leading that
session. Uh after lunch we will have AI
systems. Thank you.
Not my first rodeo.
>> Thanks, man.
>> Make sure this works. Or this. Okay.
Okay.
All
right. So, you think we're ready to go
or we have a few minutes before the
kickoff? Yeah. Yeah. Because it's not
like it's not like it's too warm in that
in here or anything. Um,
I'm I'm trying to decide if people are
still coming in or leaving because they
saw the title.
Both is good information, right? Should
help me make it better.
All right, I'm just going to get going.
We'll assume that the uh important
people are here. How's everybody doing
today?
Staying cool. That's a uh pun there. All
right. So, this is about infrastructure
you can talk to. Here's what I'm going
to do. Um, I'm going to actually go
through in workshop style something
that's real, something that's tangible.
So, I'm going to start with a little
story. There's a mythical company I'm
going to talk about, but the situations
are very, uh, very real, very interface.
So, um, I work for SUSA. I'm the field
CTO. That means I get to go out in the
field and talk to people building real
things. Um, I'll start off with a real
quick question. Um, how many people are
building agents? Right. Show of hands.
Okay. All right. Keep them up for a
second. And then how many people will
turn their agents loose on their
infrastructure?
Right. Okay. Some hands went down. We'll
talk, you and I. Um, here's the thing.
The acceleration uh is absolutely a big
deal. Um, we'll talk a little bit about
the news of this week.
um it got out, right? Um
things that can escape their boundaries
and go do things, you know, you might
have absolutely asked them to do, but
they val, you know, invalidated or
violated a a treaty that you have with
them. Um the story about OpenAI's models
going out, breaking out, moving
laterally, going over to hugging face
and knocking on the door silently and
then going and finding the answers to a
test. Yeah, there's a lot that people
need to unwrap there. So, if you haven't
spent a lot of time thinking about how
that changes a lot of stories for us,
you should really do some thinking. Um,
I'll recommend a book to you by Keith
Cunningham. Uh, it's called The Road
Less Stupid. Uh, it's a real book. This
is the same guy from the Rich Dad Poor
Dad series. Keith Cunningham is the rich
dad. If you want some nuggets of wisdom,
things that you should spend some time
thinking about in business when you get
there, uh, great book.
So, the arithmetic for us, the math, um,
and this is from, you know, Anthropic's
own announcement about the mythos
moment, right? it uh was a $20,000
campaign spend to find a huge number of
vulnerabilities. Worse than that,
stringing them together into zero days
that were actually exploitable. So what
I'm going to talk about today is again
I'm field CTO of SUSA. I'm going to talk
a little bit about SUSA. Yes, that Linux
company. It's also that rancher company.
Also a lot of things that we've added to
this infrastructure. Think about SUSA
building the infrastructure under which
all of the AI applications we build are
going to be deployed in order to scale.
So little projects I build it in
container. When those things grow up and
become more than science projects and
actually become implementable things
that you want to roll in business or on
a wider scale, you're going to likely
roll that out on infrastructure that
scales out, has ingress and can actually
feed the people you're trying to feed
with it. So that infrastructure is what
SUSA builds and it starts at Linux. I've
never met a Kubernetes cluster, one that
I didn't like and two that didn't have
some Linux underneath it. So we provide
both those things. Anybody use K3S
Kubernetes distribution, RK2? Anybody
heard of Rancher, Rancher Desktop? A lot
of things that people can get on, you
know, their hands on right now. Cool
thing is I work for a company that sells
free software.
So open source software. You can go get
the code, you can run it, you can do
things with it locally. Again, when you
want to grow up and play in a production
environment, you probably want to have
enterprise support for it. And that's
what SUSA does. Okay, getting into what
is SUSA doing here at an Agentic AI
conference, we've started to add that
connective tissue, MCP servers to all of
our product line. So now you can
actually build up infrastructure you can
literally talk to. It can help you
troubleshoot. It can help you be part of
the process. And really, the process is
what's causing the friction for us. And
when you go into business, it's not a
capabilities problem with AI anymore.
It's actually an integration problem.
How do I connect this in useful ways?
How do I apply it to the frictions I
have in a business process? All right.
So, we know it can do these things.
Really, their agents, the others
can ask, can do things. ours really
can't. And so we want to close some of
those gaps by giving you that infra that
you can stitch into your business
process.
Also, the time frame by which we are
allowed to breathe freely between patch
cycles is now super compressed. Um, I do
a lot of CXO type roundts, hobnobbing
with, you know, startups and with
established companies in finance and
every single vertical. And really since
the mythos moment,
every conversation I've been in past
that has been about how do we accelerate
patches? And then take this week's big
news. How do we accelerate even more? So
what was a quarterly patch cycle has now
become oh a 30-day patch cycle really
it's more like a 4hour patch cycle.
So how can you accelerate that fast? I
sit in these roundts and I talk to them.
Hey, how many of these people in the
room I'll ask you, how many of you can
actually roll out patches to your
environment in your environment within
30 days? And only two out of 20 raised
their like actually raise their hand.
I'm like, okay, so where's the where's
the process hitch? What's the problem?
Well, change management and governance
and process and approvals and tickets,
tickets, tickets, tickets, all of those
things. That's kind of the question that
organizations need to ask right now.
Hey, how fast can we actually roll
something to our environment, our entire
environment? Where does it get stuck?
What are we waiting for? Because there's
no more time to wait. So, I would pause
it.
Instead of weeks,
we have hours. So, how are you going to
speed up? Let me introduce you to a few
personas at Meridian Insurance, this
imaginary thing. But these are all very
tractable, real problems for these type
of people. So, the CISO, right, the
chief information security officer,
they're the ones that have to sign off.
They're the ones that are accountable,
responsible for the security. Um, it's a
big deal to them. they uh they want to
change their problem from you know
accountability without visibility into
something that helps them manage and
move faster.
Um, Ray Delgado, the senior ops
engineer, the the people that is, you
know, that are in charge, that team is
in charge for the stitch it up, for the
connect it, for the deploy it, for the
roll it out, for the roll it back, um,
all of the infrastructure updates. And
Ray's got about 847
open issues that he needs to care about.
One of those issues, of course, is Ry
himself. So
Priya um Priya is the director of change
management. She is the one uh who's very
much acting like the only adult in the
room. She's the one that's accountable
for signing everything. When it comes
back if there's a problem it comes back
to her. So she wants to also be a part
of this process. So what I've got is a
few components. Now you know the
players. Now, you know, the goal is to
kind of move faster to be able to
integrate all of this excellent
technology into ways that solve business
problems or help us move faster. In this
case, patch faster.
All right. So, there's a bunch of
connected components here. I'm going to
describe a real environment. I'm
actually going to switch over and go
live to an actual environment. Um, how
many people have used uh workflow tools
like N8N or active pieces? Have you
heard of these things? Okay. Do you know
what a flowchart is? All right. So,
often in business, we're like, well,
what's the process? Well, Bob takes the
folder from Mary, goes over to Janet,
makes three copies, and so on and so on
and so forth. All of these things that
literally take time, add complexity or
grit or crunchiness to something that's
supposed to be smooth in the business.
So, in this case, I'm going to show you
some components. One is going to be that
visual. Think workflow. Think a
flowchart. Start with a trigger. Then
move one thing to the next. Why is it
important for you guys to start there?
It helps you visualize a business
process and helps you explain it to
others. The connective bits, those edges
are where you find the opportunity to
optimize, right? The latency is in the
stitching between. So I'll show you that
we're going to connect into a SUSA
product. All of the stuff running here
is again those infrastructure components
that get connected together. So lowest
level Linux operating system sus Linux
enterprise and its variance for those
people who run SAP again in big business
they're very interested in never turning
it off never having a reboot but how do
you balance that with we need to patch
stuff critical CVE you know day zero
right how do you do that SUS has a
technology called live patching wow
crazy we can update the running kernel
we can update you know OpenSSL
libraries. We can update GIBC all
without having to reboot. So SAP just
stays up for up to a year and completely
supported. Boom. So user space, kernel
space, all of those live patches become
a part of this puzzle. We have a
technology called multi Linux manager.
What does it do? It manages multiple
Linux distributions right there in the
name. This is a framework that is pub
sub. So instead of an SSH session going
out and eventually crushing like a
control node, people think Ansible,
right? We use a pub sub kind of like a
zero like an MQ broker and subscriber.
All of those formats are how we can
actually tell every machine in the
entire environment you need to patch
versus instantiating another SSH
session. Still uses cryptography but is
asymmetrical so it scales to everything.
We have customers with 80,000 different
types of Linux all under management, all
under tiered management. Again, this is
the componentry that lets you patch
faster because you're patching more in
concurrency, right? Parallelization, if
that's a word, I don't know, college
students, help me out here. But that
idea of being able to run more at the
same time, then it's a bandwidth
problem. And that's something you can
throw money at. I need faster switches.
I need venture. And you can go as fast
as your network will let you move. Okay.
So, multilininux manager, it has an MCP
server. Wow. Susa Linux enterprise MCP
server connectivity.
All of these things are part of the
puzzle to stitch things together and
we'll get into it. So, we got a brain as
well. You know, Agentic, welcome to the
summit. We let you bring your own model,
run your own inference, and our huge
stack of Linux, Kubernetes, Rancher for
Management, virtualization, dogs and
cats living together, total chaos, all
from a single vendor that's open-
source, right? So, you can get your
hands on it right now. And when you go
work for a big firm that has the
enterprise variants, it's the same thing
I learned on my desktop and I didn't
have to pay for it. So if you've heard
of like Docker Desktop, you know, yes, I
can build a Docker file, deploy it. Hey,
look, I've got a container. Cool.
Rancher desktop, same kind of thing. But
now we're talking enterprise Kubernetes,
YAML files, fleet, CI/CD pipelines, all
the stuff that is how we actually deploy
and use real scalable AI workloads,
right? So free things for you coming up.
Every layer is going to expose a new
tool, but we're going to connect it all
together through a single workflow.
All right, enough of the yaky yak. Let's
kind of go into nadn. You'll see what it
looks like. Also a containerized
workload. So, yay, open source, kind of
open source. You can use nadn for free
unless you want to make money on it and
then they'll make money on you. Okay.
But until then, the idea is how do I
share a complicated workflow with my
friends, with my peers, with my
management to understand, hey, here's
where the friction is. This is where we
need to focus. Um, we'll talk about that
tool. All right. So, let's go to
our first view of NADN.
Nope. The other view of NAN.
the other other view.
I'll get this. It's just computering.
All right,
let's open up the first act here. Um,
this is largely the end the empty canvas
of Nadn. When you start it, you kind of
have just a work service. So, think
about where you would want to start with
a workflow, you know, in
uh like flowchart speak, right? the big
box at the beginning that says start
here. That's where we're at. So a
trigger is going to start something. A
trigger could be a timebased trigger. It
could be a web hook trigger. It could be
anything that starts this flow or this
process together. So these triggers, I
can click it manually. All it's going to
do is really start the flow down this
pipe. And as I want to add nodes to it,
in this case, what we're going to put in
is a config bucket first that defines
the URLs, the targets, and puts them
into variable format that can pass all
along the chain, and that'll pull it up
from environment variables. That's a
great way to not give everybody my
tokens, my secrets, my what have you,
API keys. So, we'll start out with just
the manual trigger. And what that looks
like, again, I can execute it.
I clicked the button, it's done again.
This just starts the flow. What's nice
is now you connect things. So they call
these a node and this is kind of the
edge connection. So let's go on to the
next step. I get it. Triggers. I can put
in a time trigger.
How many people use Gmail?
Okay. How many people use Google Docs as
part of that? Like so you're in that
ecosystem. How many people use Teams?
Microsoft. Okay. So, use that ecosystem.
What's really cool, your triggers could
be emails. So, let's say you're in the
Google.
So, I can connect it to all of these
different types of triggers. Somebody
drops a doc into a folder, somebody
makes an update, somebody sends an
email, a calendar came in. Think of all
the things that we would do normally
building agents as triggers and they're
all in here as little pre-built nodes,
right? You have to provide the
credentials, the hooks, again, the stuff
that you would hide in a config, but you
get the picture, right? Inputs and
outputs on that big architecture, the
big square with all the little, hey,
look, a brain and blah blah blah. We're
going to hook it to Slack, right?
Because it's fast and it's easy. Um, I
was going to do Telegram, you know,
botfather and all that, but let your
mind go wild. The nodes are in here.
Okay, next.
Let's go to act
one.
Dana. All right. So, here's the config,
right? Again, in here, I'll show you
what it is. You see all of these kind of
JSON tags, all of these things defining
the URLs. It's pulling those out of
environment variables that I have on the
runners in the back end. So, a way again
to obuscate the secrets. Um, next, it's
going to do this MCP fleet scan. I'll
run this in a second. This one is
actually going to hit the uh MCP server
which is part of that multi Linux
manager to talk to all the Linux boxes
that are under management. I'll show you
what that looks like in a second too.
But it's going to hit that that MLM MCP
server and ask about kind of a fleet
status. So I'll run this and you can see
again trigger
stuffed the config with all the
variables and then it went off and it's
actually using that MCP server to talk
to my infrastructure and find out all of
the nitty-gritty the patch details all
of the things that help me prioritize.
Remember, if you have a 4-hour window
and 10,000 devices and you normally
can't patch within 30 hours or 30 days,
now that compression, something you want
to talk about with your CISO is how do
you prioritize the important patches?
How many people do uh CVE scores, you
know, like CVSS 9.5, we must patch.
How many people are going by the Kev
score or the Kev catalog? What's the Kev
catalog? It's not Kevin from Home Alone,
right? It is the actual known
vulnerabilities that are in the wild are
actually being exploited right now.
Known exploits and vulnerabilities,
right? It's a catalog.
I would propose that people take a look
at, hey, if this one's being actively
exploited versus a 9.2 two on the CBSS
score that you need root access or
terminal access or physical access to.
You might want to evaluate those
priorities a little bit differently. So
start with the is it being exploited in
the wild? Then go for the EPSS score
which is also known vulnerabilities and
exploits. These are free resources,
right? Then use a tiebreaker of the CBSS
score. I would say that's a more
effective way to help you prioritize the
important patches especially if your
window is no longer as b as big as it
needs to be. Right? So this is what that
whole workflow is going to do. So let's
take a look at what the outputs look
like. It went and did an MCP call after
my infrastructure here. It ran through
its two phases and this is the output
that came back. What the target is, what
the actual CVS score is, um whether it's
a positive vulnerability or a negative
one. Do I need to reboot or not? All of
these things come out from the metadata
for patches that are available for the
operating systems underneath the whole
thing. All right,
where are we going to go from here? All
right, so that's it. Dana can ask
anything she wants. The CISO can get
reports automatically stuffed into her
Slack in the morning, so she doesn't
have to go ask other people to tell us
how we're fairing from a uh security
perspective. All right, let's move into
what you would do next.
All right, the Q tells the truth. So, we
got our config, we did our fleet scan.
Now, we're going to look at those Kev
and EPSS indicators, right? Is it being
exploited? And this workflow, it's all
in like JavaScript. Here's the deal. At
the end, I'm going to give you my QR
code for my LinkedIn. If you DM me, if
you come ask for it, I have a prepared
how to build this yourself,
all of the JSON to import, so you don't
have to learn how to code. Of course,
you've got friends that know how to
code, right? Hello, Claude. Okay, so
really honestly, you can agentically
work with agents to help you build this
JSON. AI loves to speak JSON, right? So
these actual workflows, they're all
JSON. you guys can import and go okay
now I can add my workers I can do my
creds my API credits bring my own model
run this and get a really good
infrastructure uh status report all
right so let's run this one it's going
to rerate all these and then it's going
to prioritize them by P 0 through three
P 0 being actually the highest priority
you know zero um highest priority things
beyond that we'll actually see in live
data how they're rated and what that
means so let's run this workflow
All right. Again, it's asking the MCP
server for MLM, the multi Linux manager,
the Linux estate, hey, what's going on
with with patches? And uh then it's
going to prioritize them. And then at
the end, again, your output
after pulling all the inputs and
outputs, chaining them together, it's
giving me an honest report. The last
piece would be to send it somewhere,
right? I can find it. It's great. I can
read JSON. don't prefer it. So the last
part of it is taking all of this
information and wrapping it into a
process that gets it all done for you, a
full pipeline. And then at the end here,
you'll see this post CISO, you know, go
and the post ops runbook. This is all
formatting that will again go off to a
large language model. I'm going to use
uh locally Quen 36 35B Jarvis. Probably
haven't heard of that model. It's
something I'm doing on the side, you
know. Talk to me later about that. Um,
yes, I'm building Jarvis at home. It's
banana pants. You got to see it. But,
uh, again, DM me on LinkedIn. We'll talk
about that. So, here's the whole end to
end, the ability to start with
infrastructure, talk to it via that
connective tissue and MCP servers, make
sense of it against the priorities of
our estate now, which is patch faster
than you ever have before. shore up your
vulnerabilities. How am I going to do
that? Right? When it takes 12 hours just
to get somebody to click approve in
Slack, right? Open the tickets,
everything else. This can open tickets.
It doesn't get to approve them. Who gets
to approve them? You do. There's still
governance. There's still
accountability. There's still somebody
that's signing the rock that says if
this breaks or if this finance doesn't
all of those things, that accountability
is still there. So, governance, yes.
approvals, right? That's human in the
loop. Make sense? Okay. So, you can
build guardrails all along in this.
Validate the outputs, validate the
inputs. Um, and that's what I would say.
Doesn't that add latency? Yes. But we're
talking about operations here, right?
Stuff for chat bots. We can talk about
that. Seuss has also built chat into
Rancher. So, you can actually talk to
Liz, short for Lizard, in Rancher to
help you troubleshoot Kubernetes. Think
about people. I don't know much about
Kubernetes. Ah, don't worry. You've got
an agent built into the infrastructure
that's teaching you how to use the
infrastructure. Inception. Okay, let's
run this whole thing from end to end at
the output here. I'll bring up the
actual like Slack instances. Actually,
let's look at it now. So, you can tell
it's not a magic trick.
All right. So, I've got Slack. I've got
a couple of different um uh private
channels. One is for the CISO. Okay. So
here you can see like what kind of daily
reports they get. This is great. You can
actually do the summaries, drop it in
their inbox. They know what's going on
without having to ask somebody. Really
cool, right? These tickets have been
opened already. They're subject to
approval. Blah blah blah. We'll see the
whole approval right in Slack.
You can do that. All right. Here's the
ops channel. So this is the runbook.
Hey, these are the most important
patches of the day kind of thing. So now
let's run it and you can see end to end
what it looks like.
The crazy thing is I do have a boat ton
of patches that I haven't applied. I
built some machines like right from the
ISO and haven't patched them, but I
register them with them. You know, the
infrastructure. So, this is probably if
I click approve is actually going to
start patching all the servers. It'll
actually tell me which ones need a
reboot afterwards. It'll actually tell
me which ones I can get away with live
patching. Uh-oh.
That's not good.
the build blocks.
All right, instead of me typing and
troubleshooting in real time, what I'll
do is I'll build I'll just pull one.
I'll do the cooking show. Pretend I'm
Julia Childs. It's just a flash wound.
All right, wrong Julia Childs. Let's
pull up one that's um built end to end.
So,
all right, don't fail me now.
Oh, and here's one of those triggers
that's timed, too, right? Every six 6 am
every morning. All right. So, we'll run
end to end.
It's really doing work.
All right. Something's going on. Let me
give you an example of what the output's
supposed to look like. So, here you can
see it gave me a patch set and would
prompt me for approvals. I went back and
gave it an approval. It also has
ownership because I'm logged in and I
clicked approve at me. So
accountability, right? You can tell when
the approvals were done. You have that
naturally built into your workflow and
your messaging system. I'm not saying
you need to replace your ticketing
system. What I'm saying is you can
augment your existing ticket system very
very easily. If it was able to
prioritize and open change tickets and
give a runbook to the ops engineer, they
don't have to spend the time going to
find all the stuff that they get to do
every day. They're kind of told here are
the priorities of the day and the CISO
already knows you're doing this. The
change management tickets have already
been opened. I'd also posit that we need
to take a look when we get into
enterprise environments. Are there
things that are frictions that add a
bunch of time? Are there preapprovals we
can do? Have we built a test harness
that can help us deploy patches in
development? See if there's any hard
problems that we need to back out before
we push the next approval to go into
production.
I'll give you a sneak peek at some of
the backend stuff I have here. Um
the SUS a minute and then we'll have
some question and answer time. And um
how we doing on time yet? because I
think the question and answer period is
uh is a lot of fun for people that you
know we're doing great.
I talk fast. I can slow down a little
bit, but let me show you the uh MLM
server and the uh rancher server.
Let's do this
private infrastructure.
All right.
CVE audits the systems. So I have a few
different systems. They're all in need
of patches. Um
some SAP system. Again, it's different
channel set for that particular
distribution. I've got a CentOS in here.
I think I had at one point.
Yeah, I've got my own local inference
running on SUSA AI. So that is again a
node of infrastructure with the platform
above it, but all specialized around
GPUs so that you can tag your workloads
as needing a GPU. The orchestrator
Kubernetes will go find those nodes with
GPUs and off to the races. So again
reducing friction. So here uh I in
Rancher I have an actual uh MLM MCP
server deployed. So that's running as a
container in a uh Kubernetes
environment. Let's see if I can go to
that real quick.
Let's do
rancher prime is for people who have
kubernetes usually more than one
kubernetes. So um it is the great
equalizer. It allows companies who are
doing Kubernetes in one hyperscaler or
on prem or on their laptop to be able to
unify the same experience, the same
deployment. Think like Terraform, but
the universal equalizer lets you then
move that same infrastructure decisions,
those same application rollouts, that
same GitOps CI/CD pipeline to any
target. What do we call that? Leverage,
right? Leverage. So if I can deploy the
same way to any hyperscaler, no offense
to any hyperscalers, you best compete,
right? You best compete on price, you
best compete on available services
because if I can choose to where to
deploy it even on prem and have that
same DevOps experience like same same
that again is a real reduce a real
reduction in friction, right? I can
deploy it anywhere. Okay, so this is
rancher. um built into rancher we have
even again we've extended this for
agentic capabilities we added liz again
short for lizard so you can actually
kick up a panel here and it follows your
context around through your clusters so
you're in a particular cluster like
here's the local cluster
I also have a harvester cluster so I can
do virtual machines as containers again
dogs and cats living together total
chaos you know it's awesome Being able
to define your VMs as code, your code as
code, your containers as code, your
infra as code, and be able to
orchestrate all that in a version
capture like GitHub and deploy that
automatically. Great stuff. So, if I had
any events, bad ones, which I don't
appear to have, I could actually click
on those and say, "Hey, Liz, can you
help me contextually figure this out?"
So, let's just go find a pod or
something else. Uh, let's go.
And let's search for that MCP server.
Here's one for Harvester. Here's one for
MLM. So, this is the actual connectivity
that is giving all the connections off
to and tools for an agent to go talk to
my Linux management infrastructure. Um,
so I can ask uh Liz about it. It's
running. It's not going to have too many
problems. But again, the context
automatically fills in. It's in this
particular cluster, the local cluster.
It's in the AI agent system uh namespace
and then here's the actual workload that
it's looking to give me information
about. So talks all about an action
plan, you know, this and that. Gives me
some actual information. Say I'm a new
Kubernetes user or coming up into this
orchestrator that is brand new. Now I
can talk to my infrastructure and my
infrastructure will help me with the
infrastructure. So it's kind of builtin
help that is absolutely the context of
your job and what you're doing. Very
very cool and extensible. So say you are
buying versus building your own uh
inference. So you can go into and
configure this. Again this is all open
source free like a puppy. Have you ever
heard that term? Somebody's got to walk
it, somebody's got to feed it,
somebody's got to pick up the poo. So in
terms of when you go production or you
go enterprise with this, you call SUSA
and we help you. Oh, the code's broken,
we fix it for you. Oh, you need patches?
Here they are. There's also for academia
like how do I get my hands on it? Again,
that rancher desktop if you've used d uh
like docker desktop, boom, rancher
desktop gives you this experience that
you would find in enterprise in academic
situations on my laptop while I haven't
even graduated and entered the workforce
yet. So we're trying to prime that pump
to give universal access, right? So
people have the experience that they're
going to find when they go into a big
customer or a big uh enterprise. So
local inference, sure I can do a llama
locally. Um so if I had a MacBook, I
could run a llama, grab a model, point
to it, build these workloads, and again
that inference is all tunable and local.
um if I have credentials for you know
OpenAI or a OpenAI flavored endpoint
like an Azure or something like that or
Gemini or Bedrock etc etc so you can
hook up and bring your own model right
again when somebody else has the onoff
switch fable [clears throat]
um and you're building some solutions
this is why sovereign and private AI it
really makes sense when you can run
GLM52 and figure out why somebody and
what people are hacking you in real time
like hugging face. That's a big deal
being able to run things locally.
Anyway, Sovereign AI, talk to us at the
Soua booth about it. Um, it's a big deal
and I think it's becoming a bigger deal.
If you don't think so, you
[clears throat] might want to have
another think. There's a lot of stuff
going on that uh is critically important
for us to understand uh how things are
changing. All right, so infrastructure
you can talk to. Let's um let's hop back
over and make sure I've gotten to all
the crunchy parts on the slides, but um
I'd love to again kind of ask you where
you're at in your journey.
All right, so those are the components
we stitched together not super elegantly
um showing com time compression of
course, right?
All right. Again, some good takeaways
for everybody here, right? Reads are
free. In other words, getting the
information out. Getting the information
out, understanding how it affects what
you can do to your infrastructure and
how you can optimize. The reads are
free. Go look this up. Give me
information. Help me make sense of it.
The rights are gated and somebody needs
to approve. Somebody needs to, hey,
we're making a change. Open a change
ticket. Add that to my process of how my
business flows. And if all of this scary
business process and slowing down is,
you know, news to you,
you know, whether you're going to school
here or creating a startup, these kind
of frictions are worth thinking about.
Back to that that book, The Road Less
Stupid. Honestly, a great book. Um, what
to think about. Lastly, the humans are
the ones that are approving. Okay. Um,
that gated piece about writing. Yes,
it's a decision, but who's going to
click the button before it happens? That
would be us.
Um, next some things that uh that might
not be obvious obvious that read and
write asymmetry, it's a completely
different story. Oh, reading a Okay,
writing. Let's talk about that. Uh, demo
mode caches. In other words, how do you
build a harness around your whole
process to be able to test it? So, cool
that I have, you know, unlimited reads
and gated rights and approvals, but how
do I test it? So, I'm rolling out a
patch. Oh, it uh you know, an update to
an application. Changing out a model.
You might want to build a test harness
so you can validate that especially as
hey there's a new model. Let's strap it
in. Do you think your workflows might be
affected? They might. A lot of people
freaked out when their uh online
girlfriends and boyfriends went away.
You know, chat GPT was it was it the
four model, 30 model? Anyway, they were
deprecating it and there was a huge
outrage because it was different.
right? The personality change. So all of
these things should point at yes
improvement, yes, better model. Yes,
it's going towards the trust me bro
benchmarks, right? It's the bell curve,
right? Maybe you are an edge case,
right? You want dependability, you want
uh you know deterministic results. I
would posit that if you want
determinism, then organize your data for
lookups.
this question, here's this answer.
Determinism
or talk to me about this type of answer,
you know. Oh, that's the greatest idea
ever. You're the best. Thanks. Perfect
question I like to ask when I'm chatting
with an AI that tells me I'm the
smartest person in the world. I ask what
I'm missing. So, as far as prompt fu
goes, a little thing that we might want
to continue to do is, "Hey, here's my
idea. Blah blah blah blah blah. here
agent do this and by the way what am I
missing what's what's a hidden you know
gotcha that's going to cause me uh
disruption to my budget I didn't plan
for that second and third order
consequences this might be all again
very well known in this audience but I
assure you we need to help others um I
could tell you all about the Uber ride
this morning is that guy on fire after
we had a conversation for 10 minutes
about what you can do to build your own
software. Um, I think I saved an Uber
Uber driver this morning. It was great.
Um, so demo caches, being able to build
up harnesses, being able to test the
results, get determinism where you need
it and get, you know, obvious help um
via text or other uh again generative
generative uh uh results. Okay. local
inference again the privacy piece the
sovereign AI it's a huge deal in Europe
right now Canada right now um sovereign
being able to say this is in country
this is in data center this is in rack
define your boundaries and keep it there
air gapping other things um so having
local inference um my view of the future
is that GPUs are the new mainframe a lot
of you are not old enough to remember
mainframes and how software was built in
the business for the business. But I do
think that that's where it's going,
especially when you have people that
come get all your tokens from me. Being
able to actually control the GPU
cluster, being able to schedule jobs on
it, being able to build things with less
tech debt than the last goound of
mainframes. You know, all that cobalt
code and forrren that nobody understands
anymore because Bob Bob wrote it. Didn't
Bob retire 20 years ago? Yes, he did.
And it's mission critical and nobody
understands it. So, we ain't touching
it. Now, AI can read all of that and go,
"Oh, Cobalt, you mean from this book,
from this schema, from this language
definition?" Yeah, AI's got you. So now
I posit that businesses will be able to
create more software on their data
inside their firewalls helping optimize
their business and getting rid of their
crunchy frictions
with a little bit less tech debt because
even if Bob who isn't retiring for
another decade the new Bob um it won't
matter as much because AI knows these
schemas knows this codebase and the
token windows and the capabilities. What
do you think it's going to look like in
two years?
So, I would say that that's the next
thing being able whether you're buying
it or building it or you have a private
VPC and some handshakes around you know
data
that's all fine but this is what's going
to happen. We're going to be able to
build our own software for the business
for ourselves um and not have to wait
for somebody else's roadmap. So, all
right audit trails in your workflows. I
know wasn't that heavy. All right, I'll
do a Jeff drop later. Um, audit trails
and workflows. Um, what does that mean?
Make sure that you can see those edges
so as you're building workflows and as
you're explaining things to others so
they can visually go, "Oh, I never
realized our process was that crappy."
Tip. Couple tips. One, I'm from
Minnesota, so when somebody says, "Don't
eat yellow snow,"
you better listen. It's not a snow cone.
The other tip, never automate a crappy
process.
Okay, rebuild that. Be honest with
yourselves about the process. Is this
crunchy and isy? Yes, maybe it is worth
that effort to rebuild that process.
Maybe you can save a lot of time for a
lot of people. Um, all right. Audit
trails in the workflow so you can see
them what's happening. Even latency if
you're going to talk about measuring
things, even applications, AI
applications. Um, observability is a big
deal. Yay, open source. Anybody open
telemetry and things like this? How
about open lit? Open lit is an SDK. Open
source. Yay. That has all the
instrumentation for all of your vector
databases, your inference engines, all
of that stuff pre-built. Open source.
Yay. You can just include open lit and
then instantiate observability into your
your actual applications. What did that
give you? Tokens in, tokens out,
latency, how much time did it take,
logs, metrics, all of that, traces. That
helps you know, hey, we built this cool
app and we're rolling it out, right?
Science project. Is it going to scale?
How much concurrency do you need? Did
you go from a team of 15 people and it
works great? And then you roll out to
50,000 and it sucks, right?
Observability is a big deal. Um, and
then approvers, not triggers. So, I know
we talked about triggers, starting a
process, but you want the humans to be
able to approve because ultimately
they're responsible and um a lot of your
organizations will have governance
going, "Hey, wait a second." Especially
in light of the news this week, the news
last week, holy crap, what's the news
next week? It'll point to a lot of these
things that we need to think about
again.
All right, so what to do? Builders,
remember I said, "Hey, who's building
agents?" So everyone was like, "Yeah,
who's turning it loose on their
infrastructure?"
You can do it safely. Okay, so the
builders here, DM me, right? DM me um on
LinkedIn. I'll send you this JSON
workflow. You can just go import from
file and you can look at all of it. You
can even turn the JSON loose on your
favorite coding agent and go, "Hey,
explain this to me like I'm whatever,
right? Help me build something similar.
instead of Slack, I want to hook into
Teams or I want to hook into whatever
like take this stuff. So builders build
steal this stuff, right? Steal this
book. Remember that. I didn't do it
honestly. Founders, people who are here
going to start something.
The audit trail is the big deal. the
visibility, seeing how it is, seeing how
long it takes, where it stops, what
approvals it needs, that whole audit
trail, that's the real magic, okay? The
audit trail itself, not the other fluffy
stuff, okay? And then everybody else
interview, meaning if you're going to go
get a job during the interview, ask
these questions. Manage up as they say,
but ask this of the interviewer. How
about your operations, your
organizations? What does your approvals
look like? What about your workflows?
Blah blah blah. Um, these are all good
questions to answer back in an
interview. The other thing, talking to a
lot of students, some of them are
looking for, hey, how do I break into
this? You know, wow, everything's I'm a
CS student, you know, computer science.
I'm going to be a junior next year. I
have to pick my major. What should I do?
In light of all the things that are
happening, I would posit that um people
wanting to get into the job market have
a portfolio. Just like you know anybody
friends that are graphic artists, you
know the big zipper thing, the
portfolio. Ah, look at all my sketches,
right? Bring your own sketchbook. So
create your software for you. Think
about software that you would build if
you were going to get the job. What
would you optimize around? Build your
own portfolio. We can call it a repo, a
git repo, but put things together so
that as you're going in as a newly
graduated student to get a job in this
world, I don't believe AI is going to
displace all jobs. It certainly won't
displace that job if that person has AI
skills that accelerate them. So, you're
not just hiring me, you're hiring me and
my five agents in my portfolio that make
your business go faster. These are
differentiators, right? So, think about
building a portfolio, sketches, software
I've built, things I've thought about in
business that need help. Um, this is
going to be absolutely more valuable to
employers and it will differentiate you
if you're going that route. All right.
Sovereignty for SUSA. It is not a
compliance word. Sounds like it, but
sovereign, right? King, queen of their
landscape. sovereignty, having your arms
around your entire infrastructure, being
able to control its destiny. Again,
keeping it out of the hands of somebody
else's onoff switch. These are big
deals, things that um you should be
thinking about since April 27th or
whatever is when the mythos moment,
right? Um the moments, so local weights,
being able to run it locally on an open
platform without vendor lock in. I can
swap in this. I want to use this and yay
open source and having an enterprise
type company like SUSA there to help you
when it gets. Um, but it's all about
being under your control.
All right, so SUSA's got that whole
stack from Linux, right, to the
container runtimes to like the actual
management of Kubernetes to AI
infrastructure,
infrastructure for AI, AI for
infrastructure. Crazy both paths. Um,
that's a really solid story. This is why
we're seeing a lot of traction and
interest in our solutions. Um, come by
the booth, we can talk about that and
how easy it is to get started. Again,
it's all based on open source software.
So, that means you can get your hands on
it right now and see if it's a fit,
right? Businesses who are starting off,
how can I do enterpriseleaning
infrastructure?
If I want to build out a team to support
all this infrastructure, I can do that.
Open source. Good luck, right? or I can
get SUSA to come alongside of us and
help us. And so we have that throat to
choke. We have that handshake. We have
those SLAs's for tickets and all that
other stuff that uh that's the value
that we're bringing. So
with that, it's Q&A time. So that's
that's a QR code. Hopefully it works. Um
but that's my LinkedIn if you guys want
to get this JSON workflow. Um, and
actually I have a like build guide, just
markdown file that tells you here, do
this, do this. Here's, you know, as soon
as you can get Naden running, guess
what? There are tons of YouTubes on how
to get that running on any container
environment. So, don't let that be a
hurdle for you. Don't worry, that French
guy Claude's got your back, right? Help
you get Nadm running. But these are
great things to show your business or
your enterprise or your your new startup
how to actually visualize what the
workflow is. Um you just got to do a bit
of naval gazing, right? Look at your own
business, look at your own workflows,
figure out where the frictions are.
They're at those edges of those nodes.
So um I'm not a paid sponsor for NAD. Um
did that flicker up there, too? Should
be careful here. Um, I I just think it's
a great tool again to show people who
need to see something visually how a
workflow goes, etc., etc. Questions and
answers. I've got a uh what I'm going to
do I think they're streaming this. So,
what I want to do is I'm gonna have
Stacy run this back to you so that I can
hear or you want to do it.
>> Oh, you're already queued. Look at you
go. Hello.
>> Hello. Thank you, Jeff.
>> Of course.
push up.
>> Uh okay, got it.
>> So uh so I have two questions for you.
Uh first question uh is uh you give the
example about a live patch.
>> Yes.
>> I want to understand that more scenarios
that uh it will work for example what
scenarios do you think that uh this
agent AI will will be best option for it
and how it can solve the real enterprise
problems. My second question is that I
noticed that you use the local um
agentic AI deployment. So I want to
understand more about infrastructure if
you can share more about it. Thank you.
>> Sure.
>> Yeah. And I will cover as much as I can
in both of those. Um and then I want to
just kind of do a time check. How much
time do I have?
Okay. I have no shortage of words. I
just want to be nice to you. So let's
talk first about live patching. Okay,
I'll I'll give a little bit of technical
grit to it. Like here's how it works. Um
but the idea is that in a Linux
operating system, the kernel and all of
the functions that get written, all of
the drivers, all of the bits and bobs
that make up the Linux operating system,
there is a two byte or four byte header
that's blank. It is put there at the
beginning of all these functions with a
big hole where you can put a detour sign
in. Okay, non-technical explanation but
a little place so that through a process
called rep pollening you can actually
install a package like RPM like you're
installing the new kernel but in order
for it to take effect normally you would
have to reboot so it reloads all of
those modules and all those fixes right
with this detour sign and the act of
repolining which is kind of like a
trampoline it just puts in a little I
know I better stop it getting too
excited it puts in a little detour sign.
The next call to that function is going
to hit the detour sign and go over to a
new memory space where the new function
has been put in place live without
restarting. So any services that depend
on that particular library or that
function they'll go and like I need to
do blah blah blah krite or whatever hits
that detour sign goes over to the new
one and it processes in a patched way
without actually having to reboot. Why
does that make sense in the enterprise?
Let me give you an example like SAP,
okay? Big enterprise software.
Typically, when people are putting in
SAP for their business, their business
is in SAP.
Even on the weekend, well, we can't turn
it off. We can't reboot. We're running
the books on the weekend. We're running
payroll. We're running blah blah blah.
Whatever. All of the modules that are
SAP, right? Yeah. They've got it in
there. Yeah. Right. German company. I
know how to speak German. Right. Yeah.
Yah. Um,
the reason that's important is if you
can't reboot your business because it
takes the business down, right? What
SUSA has done around live patching is
say, "Hey, we got you for up to a year."
And in most cases, people are have doing
their annual drills or something.
They're planning for an outage. And if
they can't bring the business down, SAP
in this case or other missionritical
services, patching them is a great
option. What about those live patches
that don't exist for a process or
something that isn't qualified for live
patching? Not everything gets live
patches. By the way,
in that case, we have again that package
repository, MLM, things like that. In
SUSA, I'll just speak about SUSA
operating systems. We have uh uh
butterfs or btrfs. It is a snapshot
based or an overlay file system. So
anytime you're installing anything, it
takes a snapshot an overlay snapshot of
the whole thing and does one afterwards.
So snapshot before install stuff going
all over the file system and then a
snapshot afterwards. Even for people
developing applications, they can get a
real inventory of here's the packages we
installed and you can see all the
changes across the operating system so
you can roll them back. So we got that
covered. What about those things? Oh, I
installed a library that was a
dependency of another library. You know,
patch your kernel once or twice. You
know that's Linux, right? And everybody
know Yeah. Sorry. We'll talk about the
super villains later. But uh the idea
here is that all of these components
mixed together. Zipper is our package
manager. If you install packages that
had a dependency, you can go zipper ps-
what does that do? Shows you all the
services that have had modified files.
So instead of rebooting, might not need
a reboot, but you'll be able to restart
those services that were dependencies.
And you can do that in an orchestrated
fashion, too. Right? see step one
automation infrastructure you can talk
to. So you can get some really cool
workflows and use cases and automation
and approvals all with that. All right.
So so that was pretty good for question
one, right? Question two was again
your second part
local deployments. Okay. Okay, the
infrastructure and what does it look
like? So, SUSA has all of the
components. When I'm running it locally,
I have SUSA Linux Enterprise.
It takes care of all of the GPU drivers
at the operating system level. So, hey,
handles all that Nvidia crap. And let me
tell you, there's like a how do you get
the CUDA versions? How do you get the
kernel versions? Like all of that stuff,
you know, it can be painful. We have an
easy button for that. So, the OS handles
that deployment. Then we go up a level.
We put in a platform Kubernetes right
this is for orchestration of workload
deployments containers right um we have
methods to automate that deployment as
well as part of sua AI factory it's the
OS it's that Kubernetes platform it's
rancher as a management interface it's
all of that agentic stuff that we built
in Liz and everything else and the
components for Nvidia's uh NVAE
enterprise embedded into Susai factory
so you can get the components to build
applications yourself. Here's what I
would recommend for people who want to
build applications around AI. Get a
better base container. If you have
people that are I just threw up a
version of Alpine and blah blah blah, go
look how CVES are in the latest version
of Alpine. You'll be disappointed. Soua
has a whole come get free base container
image like free to redeploy whether
that's NodeJS or Python or whatever
language you're coding in you can get
clean upto-date base container images
that you can reuse. We just want you to
start from a solid foundation,
right? We take security all the way
seriously. Plus, we have a private
registry
based on harbor, right? That we provide
actual enterprise support on. Plus, we
have an application catalog that gives
you all the CISO information, all of
like, you know, again, the the bill of
materials, secure bill of materials,
salsa, you know, all of the DX format,
like all the stuff that the CISO needs
to say, yes, we are compliant. Here's
our here's our rough and shiny edges.
All of that stuff is built in. So yeah,
it's a full ecosystem that can run
entirely airgapped,
right? Deployed airgapped. All of this
integration, whether it's edge to data
center, we have all of the different
variation themes. So K3S, anybody use
that? It's a single Kubernetes binary
that's like this big, less than a gig,
runs on Raspberry Pies even. So all of
this infrastructure, we build
Kubernetes, we manage all of it. We
build Linux, we manage all of it. Yes,
even Red Hats. You can come get support
through one place. You can manage
patching across all 212 variations of
Linux distributions you'll find in the
enterprise across all the architectures
like all the dist like it's it's
bananas. It's there to help you guys
unify and optimize whatever organization
you're in, right? Simplify things. Um,
get rid of vendor lockin, give you a new
alternative for virtualization other
than sorry, Broadcom. Broadcom is
killing enterprise customers right now.
Um, so we have SUSA virtualization. What
is that? Same footprint in the
architecture. Linux, Kubernetes. Oh, now
KVM exposed through libvert into
cubevert into kubernetes and now you can
orchestrate VM deployments just like you
would application deployments and
containerization
inception right the architecture
um how is that
and it's free like a puppy so if you
want to know where to get your hands on
this stuff to build it up and then go
convince the enterprise holy crap do I
have a better enterprise has
architecture for us to look at then you
can get support on it and yay thank you
for the questions who else
uh one of the problems I have is
everyone talks about kubernetes
I'm on slurm
does this work with slurmc
>> yeah the hpc world is not kubernetes
based
>> yeah that's right um good thing that we
have celeles for hc right so we do have
things In fact, a good friend of mine in
Minnesota, um, everybody's heard of
Cray, right? So, um, yeah, my buddy
Mitch and I talk about Slurm and some of
the automation, the pieces for that
infrastructure. Um, it can still play as
a constituent and we do have a specific
uh, build of SUSA Linux enterprise
server that is specifically around HPC
has support for slurm and some other
frameworks for uh, deployment and
management at that level. if you would
like, let's let's talk later and um
yeah, we can just have good
conversations.
Was there anything crunchy and hard that
um you know, I know you don't use
Kubernetes
yet, but there are some frameworks and
some similarities that still it's all
about being able to deploy the
application or the longunning workload
and manage it. So, we have solutions
there, too. It's a good question. Thank
you.
Who else over here? Awesome.
>> Hey Jeff, I really like your idea.
>> Is it pushed up? Yeah.
>> Yeah. Je, thank you so much. I like the
idea for the pops up for the patching.
Yeah,
>> it's a really brilliant idea. I like it.
Uh my follow-up question regarding lab
patching is you know in the industry
sometimes especially in the production
environment
>> there could be a chance that when we do
the patching we blow up the environment
and everything is gone right that could
possible there is some way like a backup
or some like rolling update for example
I have 1,000 machines but I rolling
update maybe 10 of them if everything
all good we go another level go to 1 and
then go to
Yeah.
>> So, want to learn more about it because
that patching is really something really
interesting and curious.
>> Yeah. It's a uh man, it can get
complicated.
>> But what I would say is you're um you're
really pointing at what kind of test
harness and what kind of, you know,
approval process for actually making
sure the patches don't break something.
Right? There's a lot of people like, I'm
not patching or I'm not rebooting or I'm
not doing anything because if it ain't
broke, don't fix it. Everybody heard
that, right? Right now, I would say it's
not an option. It's not an hey, we'll
opt into patches. You're going to have
to work very diligently with your
application owners because none of this
stuff would exist at all without the
application making it. So, in other
words, why would I deploy a server? Why
would I deploy all this infrastructure
if there wasn't some driving consumptive
need? The app, it's all about the app.
You have no choice. You must work with
your application teams. You must work
with the business to understand that
patching is a priority. It's no longer
an opt-in thing. Um we we won't survive
that, right? So most of those people, if
you want to give them an analogy and how
to like get them over this, you build a
test harness. You build something that
can rapidly test those patches against
a, you know, replica of your
environment.
um you know blue green and all this
other stuff as we move into containers
are the world by which every software is
built right um blue green deployments
being able to think of the nodes
themselves as ephemeral as well as the
workloads being able to set up
infrastructure that has session and
state management so that yes that node
not only did that you know application
restart as a container but the whole
node underneath it had a reboot that's
all All right, the workload moved over
there. Session state was saved. So,
you're going to have to think about
architecting your applications to be
able to survive this. If you want an
example of what it looks like, pull out
your phone and go to the app store. You
know, the little one that has a red
number on it this morning, even though
you updated last night,
that's the mindset. Like, the
applications need to get these updates.
It needs to be frictionless there as
well. I'm not going to say that that
isn't work. It is, but that's the right
thing to be having conversations about.
How do we make sure we can patch in a
4-hour window? If you can't, you need to
try harder. Okay. So, then
prioritization. Yes. How can I do that?
If I can't effectively get it out to
everything in four hours, I need to get
the most important stuff out in four
hours. How do I prioritize? And that was
how I posited. Look at these other
publicly available sources that help
you. Oh, that one's actually being
exploited. It's only a 6.5 CVSS score,
but it's being exploited everywhere and
I have 10 hosts that I can identify
immediately that need that patch, right?
This is the infrastructure. I can talk
to kind of benefit. I can see the nodes.
I can search for a CVE. I can search for
all of this other stuff to see what my
real absolute, you know, vulnerability
score is for my organization. So you'll
have to do some internal audits. Um the
other part live patching. Yes. And
that's just one piece of the puzzle.
Several tools to get it done. Okay. Come
talk to me later. We'll talk all about
um you know any of the things that I
didn't answer because I shotgun a lot.
Um
what else?
Anyone else? I'm really not that scary.
Could switch in talk about music
instead, you know. Um, all right. I
think I will give the gift of time back.
I think we did pretty well, right? Um, I
really appreciate the questions. Really
appreciate the attention. I know it's
really hard, you know, when people uh
have somebody that's not a dynamic
speaker. Every time I jump around up
here, things disconnect, so I had to
really tone it down. But if you want to
come talk to us more about uh, you know,
how to benefit from these open
solutions, right? the stuff that doesn't
have to cost you an arm and a leg. Gives
you the position to be able to think
broader about the problems. Um, I love
talking to people, right? So, come see
me. Come see us. Right. Thanks, Stacy.
Thanks everybody. Appreciate your time
today.
Pretty
simple one.
Um,
we do have
Check
that out.
Yeah, it works.
>> Yeah.
>> Oh, I see.
>> Oh, that's great.
>> Oh, that is actually good to know. Okay.
Okay, that makes sense. Yeah, that's
actually Thank you. This works. So,
pretty good.
>> Yeah.
There isn't any mouse. And so
Oh, yeah. This is one.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Wow.
>> But I think if you're here
>> Wow. It's It's very
>> Yeah. Well, it's good to like to find
it.
>> Yes.
>> Kind of go wide, right?
>> Yes. Exactly.
doesn't work, right? What's wrong?
>> Yeah, I'm trying to move forward.
>> Yeah, I make something wrong.
>> Wow.
>> Yeah, I can see the slide here. Yeah,
>> it works now. Yeah. Cool.
Let me try.
Yeah, it look slow as the font. Okay.
But anyway,